MARÍA VALENTINA GARCÍA-ALVARADO

Bogotá, Colombia. (+57) 3134059779 mv.garcia@uniandes.edu.co https://mvgarcia.github.io/Personal-web-page/

Fifth year Physics undergraduate student and fourth year Engineering student at Universidad de los Andes in Colombia. Beginner researcher in computational Cosmology and Star Formation. Interested in acquiring knowledge on Astronomy, Astrophysics and Computer Science. Looking forward to pursuing a PhD in Astrophysics focusing my research on Galaxy formation and evolution, Star formation or Cosmology.

EDUCATION

JANUARY 2018 – CURRENTLY FIFTH YEAR (EXPECTED GRADUATION DATE: JUNE 2023) BACHELOR OF SCIENCE: PHYSICS

UNIVERSIDAD DE LOS ANDES - BOGOTÁ, COLOMBIA

JANUARY 2019 – CURRENTLY FOURTH YEAR (EXPECTED GRADUATION DATE: JUNE 2023) BACHELOR OF ENGINEERING: SYSTEMS AND COMPUTING ENGINEERING

UNIVERSIDAD DE LOS ANDES - BOGOTÁ, COLOMBIA

JUNE 2020 – TODAY
MINOR IN ASTRONOMY

UNIVERSIDAD DE LOS ANDES - BOGOTÁ, COLOMBIA

SCHOOLS

SEPTEMBER 2020

SUMMER SCHOOL ON GALAXIES AND COSMOLOGY

INSTITUT TEKNOLOGI BANDUNG, INDONESIA

Link to the school: https://www.as.itb.ac.id/ssgc2020/

NOVEMBER 2020

ASTRONOMY TWINNING PROGRAM

LEIDEN OBSERVATORY AND UNIVERSITY OF ANTIOQUIA

Link to the school: https://sites.google.com/site/astrotwincolo/home

JUNE 2021

ESCAPE SUMMER SCHOOL

EUROPEAN SCIENCE CLUSTER OF ASTRONOMY & PARTICLE PHYSICS ESFRI RESEARCH INFRASTRUCTURES

Link to the school: https://indico.in2p3.fr/event/20306/

JUNE - JULY 2021

MEXICAN ASTROCOSMOSTATISTICS SCHOOL

Link to the school: http://fisica.ugto.mx/~events/macss/

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

2018 - 2020

UNIVERSIDAD DE LOS ANDES

ADVISOR: Jaime E. Forero-Romero, PhD

The cosmic web through the lens of graph entropy

An analysis of the cosmic web using properties of graphs. Applied the beta-skeleton graph on simulated dark matter halos and measured its graph entropy. We found the correlation between the entropy and quantities such as the cosmological parameters.

JUNE - SEPTEMBER 2021

CHALMERS ASTROPHYSICS & SPACE SCIENCE SUMMER (CASSUM)

ADVISORS: Jonathan Tan, PhD. Chia-Jung Hsu, MsC.

Structural analysis of massive protoclusters formed from cloud collisions

An study of the structure of evolving massive protoclusters using properties of graphs to determine properties of the parent molecular cloud. Applied dendrogram to identify protostellar cores at different stages of evolution and compute its Minimum Spanning Tree. We computed quantities such as the mass segregation of the cluster and analyzed the spatial distribution of the cores.

Research program link: http://cosmicorigins.space/cassum21

2021

UNIVERSIDAD DE LOS ANDES

ADVISOR: Jaime E. Forero-Romero, PhD **Analyzing spectra from DESI using UMAP**

Finding anomalous spectra coming from DESI to detect failures on the instrument (specifically, physical defects in some CCDs), using Umap. Umap is a dimension reduction technique that has shown to be effective in classifying multidimensional objects into groups. Spectra coming from a CCD with failures are grouped differently.

PUBLICATIONS

The cosmic web through the lens of graph entropy. M. V. García-Alvarado, X.-D Li and J. E.

Forero-Romero, MNRAS: Letters, 498, L115, 2020.

Link to the publication: https://doi.org/10.1093/mnrasl/slaa145

Structural analysis of massive protoclusters . **M. V. García-Alvarado**, Jonathan Tan, PhD. Chia-Jung Hsu, in prep.

CONFERENCES

NOVEMBER 2019

LATIN AMERICAN IAU MEETING - ANTOFAGASTA, CHILE

TALK: BETA-SKELETON FOR THE ANALYISIS OF THE LARGE SCALE STRUCTURE OF THE UNIVERSE

Link to the event: http://www.sochias.cl/larim2019/

OCTOBER 2019

CONGRESO COLOMBIANO DE ASTRONOMÍA - MEDELLÍN, COLOMBIA

TALK: CONSTRAINING COSMOLOGICAL PARAMETERS WITH THE BETA-SKELETON OF THE COSMIC WEB

Link to the event: https://planetariomedellin.org/COCOA2019

JANUARY 2022

ORIGINS WORKSHOP – SALT LAKE CITY, UTAH.

TALK (VIDEOCONFERENCE): STRUCTURAL ANALYSIS OF MASSIVE PROTOCLUSTERS Link to the event: http://cosmicorigins.space/originsslc

OCTOBER 2020

SEMINARIO DE ASTRONOMÍA, UNIVERSIDAD DE LOS ANDES – BOGOTÁ, COLOMBIA TALK (VIDEOCONFERENCE): FINDING QSO PAIRS

AUGUST 2021

SEMINARIO DE ASTRONOMÍA, UNIVERSIDAD DE LOS ANDES – BOGOTÁ, COLOMBIA

TALK (VIDEOCONFERENCE): STRUCTURAL ANALYSIS OF MASSIVE PROTOCLUSTERS

SEPTEMBER 2020

COSMOLOGÍA EN COLOMBIA - BOGOTÁ, COLOMBIA

TALK (VIDEOCONFERENCE): THE COSMIC WEB THROUGH THE LENS OF GRAPH ENTROPY

Link to the event: https://indico.cern.ch/event/926040/

MARCH 2019

COSMOLOGÍA EN COLOMBIA - BOGOTÁ, COLOMBIA

TALK: CONSTRAINING COSMOLOGICAL PARAMETERS WITH THE BETA-SKELETON OF THE COSMIC WEB

Link to the event: https://indico.cern.ch/event/799097/

DECEMBER 2020

ICTP-SAIFR LATIN AMERICAN WORKSHOP ON OBSERVATIONAL COSMOLOGY – SÃO PAULO, BRAZIL

POSTER (VIDEOCONFERENCE): THE COSMIC WEB THROUGH THE LENS OF GRAPH ENTROPY

Link to the event: $\frac{https://www.ictp-saifr.org/south-american-workshop-on-cosmology-in-the-lsst-era/}{}$

OBSERVING EXPERIENCE

DECEMBER 2021

SUPPORT OBSERVER, DESI

Supported DESI observations for four consecutive nights.

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

AUGUST 2019 - DECEMBER 2020

TUTOR, UNIVERSIDAD DE LOS ANDES

Tutored undergraduate engineering and science students in Python programming skills.

AUGUST 2020 - DECEMBER 2020

GRADER. UNIVERSIDAD DE LOS ANDES

Graded exams from a basic physics class.

AUGUST 2021 - DECEMBER 2021

TUTOR, UNIVERSIDAD DE LOS ANDES

Tutored undergraduate engineering and science students in basic Physics topics (Basic Mechanics, Electrodynamics, Thermodynamics).

MENTORSHIP

FEBRUARY 2021 – JULY 2021

PENTA BY SHE SPEAKS SCIENCE

Participant of the mentorship program supported by the University of Cambridge and the IAU . After a competitive selection, I was one of the 33 women selected from all around the world to mentor a girl and be mentored by another woman in STEM. This program aims to create a community of empowered women by giving advice and supporting each other.

Link to the program: https://www.shespeaksscience.com/penta/

FEBRUARY 2021 - MAY 2021

MENTOR IN COMPAS PROGRAM AT UNIVERSIDAD DE LOS ANDES

Mentor at the mentorship program for students at their first semester.

SKILLS

- Proficient at Python and Java programming.
- Proficient at managing data bases with SQL.
- Wide experience using LaTeX.
- Experience on processing of N body simulations.
- Experience with version controlling using Git.
- Manage the basics of Bash.